Register of the Firing Line (Television Program) broadcast records 80040.4089238
Hoover Institution Archives
- Episode Guide, 1966-1999
  - "Do Capitalists Go Too Far?" Guests: Forbes, Malcolm S., 7 January 1988 (Item Program Number S0767, 1729)
    Program details: One of the world's most exuberant capitalists attacks the question with verve. One sample: WFB: "I think it's true that, in democracies in particular, people tend to want to punish a system because there are conspicuous people within it who, in their judgment, abuse that system. Now, would you concede that we have very conspicuous abusers of capitalism right now?" MSF: "Oh, no question. I don't know that they're worse now than they ever were, they're just on a larger take basis, they're dealing with larger sums--Mr. Boesky and Company. I really think that in this country we take the functioning of capitalism for granted, but we're not happy about those many who fall through the net. We're not happy with the unsolved problems. And it's not just villainy, there are shortcomings in capitalism."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1012
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6946
  - "Impasse in Israel" Guests: Zogby, James J.: Zion, Sidney., 19 January 1988 (Item Program Number S0768, 1730)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 128: 22
    Program details: Not a pleasant program to watch--as the animosity between the guests mirrors all too clearly that in the Middle East--but an instructive one. Two samples: SZ: "If it’s true that the PLO (Palestine Liberation Organization) is representative of the Palestinian people, they are then represented by a group that... each year passes again its charter that says: We will destroy the state of Israel. Clear cut. No doubt about it." JZ: "But Israel is involved daily in the destruction of the Palestinian national identity, occupation of Palestinian land, the deportation and expulsion of Palestinian leaders." ... WFB: "If France was prepared to receive the president of West Germany four or five years after the second of those terrible conquests, and if we could receive the people who actually bombed Pearl Harbor, it seems to me that one could hope historically that there might be some means by which the essential requirement of both peoples could be met."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1013
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6947
  - "The Libertarian Candidate" Guests: Paul, Ron, 1935-, 19 January 1988 (Item Program Number S0769, 1731)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 128: 23
    Transcript: Box/Folder 182: 9
    Program details: Dr. Paul, a former Republican, is the Libertarian Party's candidate for President, and he proves, in this energetic exchange, to be a well-spoken exponent of the libertarian creed. WFB: "As somebody who occasionally calls himself a libertarian, I regret the extent to which the libertarian position is discredited by a kind of reductionism that is simply incompatible with social life. You want to destroy the FBI, for instance. Why?" RP: "Well, we could point out, first, that the first 125 years of this country existed without an FBI. That came about, I believe, during the First World War. The CIA is a really recent phenomenon, 1947." WFB: "Well, we existed 125 years without an airplane, too."
    Availability: On amazon.com. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1014
    DVD Link: http://www.amazon.com/dp/B00ANCWV20
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6948
  - "A Tribute to Clare Boothe Luce" Guests:, 19 January 1988 (Item Program Number S0770, 1732)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 128: 24
    Program details: This is only the second time that Firing Line has paused to mark the passing of a favorite guest (the first being the tribute to Allard Lowenstein, s0415). This show includes delicious excerpts from Mrs. Luce's four Firing Line appearances, and concludes with Mr. Buckley's eulogy at her memorial Mass at St. Patrick's Cathedral in Manhattan: "Clare Luce, now at Mepkin finally, is no longer disturbed. It is only we who are disturbed, Hank Luce above all, and her friends; sad, so sad without her, yet happy for her, embarked finally, after stooping so many times to pick up so many splinters, on her way to the Cross."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1015
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6949
  - "The Pope's New Encyclical" Guests: McBrien, Richard P.: Novak, Michael., 29 February 1988 (Item Program Number S0771, 12)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 128: 25
    Transcript: Box/Folder 182: 10
    Program details: These guests, a leading Catholic liberal and a leading Catholic conservative, had been signed up before the announcement of Sollicitudo Rei Socialis, an encyclical which had been criticized by, among others, Messrs. Buckley and Novak for being, as Mr. Buckley puts it, "susceptible to the argument of moral equivalence; namely, that there are not important moral differences between the two contending blocs pursuing a cold war." Here they have as a foil Father McBrien, who does not by any means agree with his Pope on everything but does agree with him on this question. WFB: "[The Pope] said it is insufferable that people should be suffering from a lack of food anywhere in the world, while in the Midwest they are destroying food. Now I think it is insufferable morally, but I know of no way to avoid that problem. I really don't." RM: "You know what you've done, though? As a theologian I recognize what you've done, and I think it's absolutely legitimate. You've just made a distinction between a moral principle and its application."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1016
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6950
  - "Should We Legalize Drugs?" Guests: Glasser, Ira.: Stutman, Robert., 29 February 1988 (Item Program Number S0772, 1734)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 128: 26
    Program details: Changing hearts and minds on this particular issue is one of the hardest tasks in the public arena, but our guests and their host have another go at it. Each has excellent arguments, vividly presented. Do we make laws for everyone with the 12-year-old in mind? Does the War on Drugs turn people into criminals, or were a majority of users of illegal drugs criminals first? Has the War on Drugs actually--and contrary to what is often asserted--reduced the number of addicts in the United States? You pays your money and you takes your choice, but these three lay out the choices for us.
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1017
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6951
  - "Will Doctors Have to Go Out of Business?" Guests: Fischer, Lee A.: Montgomery, Robert M., Jr.: Musgrove, Martha, 15 April 1988 (Item Program Number S0773, 1735)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 128: 27
    Transcript: Box/Folder 182: 11
    Program details: A highly combative exchange among a doctor, a lawyer, and a journalist on the state of medical malpractice. As Mr. Buckley gives the background: "In Dade County, Florida, in 1987, the average malpractice insurance premium for doctors was $165,000 per year. That was up, in four years, from $30,000. In Palm Beach County ... malpractice insurance for obstetricians ... added $700 to the delivery cost for a baby. Enough, finally, was enough." Doctors walked off the job, until the legislature passed a bill altering the malpractice law. Mr. Montgomery tends to see doctors in these cases as entirely in the wrong; Dr. Fischer returns the compliment concerning lawyers. Still--thanks largely to Mrs. Musgrove--we do get an idea of the points at issue.
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1019
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6953
  - "Scare Tactics and AIDS" Guests: Fumento, Michael Aaron.: Tamarkin, Norman R., 31 March 1988 (Item Program Number S0774, 1736)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 128: 28
    Program details: As Dr. Tamarkin puts it, "This whole issue of AIDS is so sensitive politically ... it's a lightning rod for a lot of strong opinions because it has to do with seeking pleasure, with sex, with drugs, with a contagious illness for which there is no cure." Mr. Fumento is a serious student of the spread of the disease, and while his findings are far from uncontroversial (he was working on a book to be called The Myth of Heterosexual AIDS), he has the facts and figures in hand for this perhaps surprisingly low-key discussion of a highly emotional topic.
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1018
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6952
  - "The Problems of Mayor Koch, Democrat" Guests: Koch, Ed, 1924-, 28 April 1988 (Item Program Number S0775, 1737)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 128: 29
    Transcript: Box/Folder 182: 12
    Program details: WFB leads off: "Mayor Koch, one charge that you leveled against Jesse Jackson was that he was untruthful. Haven't you invited the same charge to be made against yourself? Because before the New York primary you said that under President Jesse Jackson the country would be broke in three weeks and defenseless in six. A few days later, you said that if it came to that alternative, you would vote for candidate Jackson against candidate Bush on the grounds that a President Jackson would do 'less damage' to the country than a President Bush. Were you suggesting that under President Bush the United States would be broke in less than three weeks?" And we're set for the usual delicious mix of substance and chutzpah. EK: "... regrettably, what I did was to use words that were too sharp. Jesse Jackson is more than a candidate, he is an emotional symbol to large numbers of our population, and they did not want to hear my commentary, or did not want to hear the sharp rhetoric."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1020
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6954
  - "Chile and a Novel Approach to Social Security" Guests: Pinera, Jose., 28 April 1988 (Item Program Number S0776, 1738)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 128: 30
    Program details: Soon after Mr. Pinera became Chile's Minister of Labor in 1978, he proposed a startling new idea: privatize Social Security. Perhaps even more startling, the Pinochet regime agreed, and the system has been a fabulous success. Mr. Pinera explains why, lucidly and engagingly, also explains why it would be a good idea here, and talks about the prospect of re-establishing democracy in his country. One sample, which takes on a haunting resonance in the light of the campaign launched against Augusto Pinochet eight years after he stepped down as president (see Firing Line s01190): "Basically, what the military has said is: Look, in 1973 there was this Marxist government; they were violating the constitution, it was like a tiger going around creating problems. People asked us to mount the tiger. We have mounted the tiger. We have dominated the tiger. Now we ride to decide how to dismount the tiger without being eaten."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1021
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6955
  - "Mortimer Adler on The Closing of the American Mind" Guests: Adler, Mortimer Jerome, 1902-2001., 6 May 1988 (Item Program Number S0777, 1739)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 128: 31
    Transcript: Box/Folder 182: 13
    Program details: Mr. Adler had dissented from Allan Bloom's runaway best seller (discussed on Firing Line s0735), and Mr. Buckley here invites him to explain why. As the hour plays out, Mr. Adler spends more time-as engagingly and cogently as always-on education in general and some of his own concerns in particular, though when he turns to his fellow philosopher he is illuminating: The two great political philosophers that Bloom admires most are Plato and Rousseau, and neither is a democrat in my sense of the term. Neither would take Mill's view that democracy is the ideal form of government with a long future and almost no past."
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1022
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6956
  - "Dirty Rock Lyrics" Guests: Gore, Tipper.: Simmons, Doug.:, 8 June 1988 (Item Program Number S0778, 1801)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 129: 1
    Program details: This is the first Firing Line in a new format: it runs half an hour instead of an hour, and, instead of an examiner called in somewhere past the midpoint of the show, there is a moderator, as in the Firing Line debates, who starts things off. As it happens, each of these guests is something of a Johnny One-Note (Mrs. Gore: "We have to show that we respect the First Amendment and artists' rights ... but at the same time be sensitive to young children." Mr. Simmons: "The record industry ... would love to get rid of [heavy metal].... Why worry about it?"), but Mr. Buckley is on top form: "To whip up community sentiment, whether it's against acid rain or against child abuse, is a legitimate function of social invigoration, and to suggest that because you might stumble into something that was intended to be artistic is to ask for a kind of protection that you can't legitimately hope for.""
    Availability: On amazon.com. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1024
    DVD Link: http://www.amazon.com/dp/B00TZ8GE30
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6958
  - "Who Should Be Vice President and Why?" Guests: Maslin, Paul.: Green, Mark J., 6 July 1988 (Item Program Number S0779, 1802)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 129: 2
    Transcript: Box/Folder 182: 14
    Program details: This vigorous discussion is about evenly divided between what sort of person a Vice President should be and--since our guests are both liberal Democrats--whom Michael Dukakis should pick as his running mate. (Most of the running-mate discussion is on the plausibility of Jesse Jackson, though Mr. Maslin does mention Lloyd Bentsen as a strong contender.) MG: "One point I would like to make, if I could, that we are leaving out of this equation: ... Democrats are frustrated because they have been out of the White House 16 of 20 years, and are extremely united behind Dukakis because they don't want a Reagan successor. Therefore, there will be very little moaning if Dukakis picks someone that's not ideal, unlike the Republicans, who are already complaining that Governor Tom Kean is the keynoter [at the convention], and you have Republicans like Howard Phillips and Richard Viguerie bitterly attacking Reagan and Bush. I don't think you will see that phenomenon in the Democratic Party this year."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1031
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6965
  - "The Central American Mess" Guests: Van den Haag, Ernest.: Farer, Tom J., 8 June 1988 (Item Program Number S0780, 1803)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 129: 3
    Program details: Messrs. van den Haag and Farer are the co-authors of U.S. Ends and Means in Central America: A Debate and they know their stuff--although, as their book title suggests, they disagree on what those ends and means should be. Mr. Farer takes a laid-back, laissez-faire view of the Soviets' potential installation of missiles in Latin America ("We have the means to act directly and immediately to deal with it, which ... makes it very unlikely that it would be attempted"), Mr. van den Haag takes a more pre-emptive view ("It may not be a reasonable thing for the Soviet Union to place nuclear arms in Cuba, but they did it. And I see no reason to believe they may not act equally irrationally in some Central American republic.... We should be ready"), and Mr. Buckley keeps them on track ("One can't reasonably assume that the Soviet Union is going to invest a billion dollars a year in Nicaragua, which I am told has been done for the last four years, unless they intend to do something other than to Bolshevize the bananas").
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1023
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6957
  - "Update on Drug Legalization" Guests: Grinspoon, Lester, 1928-: Szasz, Thomas Stephen, 1920-, 29 June 1988 (Item Program Number S0781, 1804)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 129: 4
    Transcript: Box/Folder 182: 15
    Program details: Guests and host all agree that drugs should be legalized, but at that point Dr. Szasz takes leave of the others (and, some would say, of his senses). Dr. Grinspoon would legalize drugs but tax them heavily, to pay for the social costs of drug use; Mr. Buckley was developing his "federal drugstore" idea, to provide drugs cheaply enough to get organized crime out of the business, but in a regulated fashion; and Dr. Szasz calls any sanctions "scapegoating." One sample: TS: "Let's take some heroin addict who, at age 25, ODs. Look at the amount of money he has saved society by not being on welfare for the next 60 years, and not being in jail and not mugging people." WFB: "But suppose he wasn't going to be on welfare. Suppose he was going to be Thomas Edison." TS: "That's unlikely that he would be so undisciplined then." WFB: "I don't think it's unlikely at all... Unfortunately there's no correspondence between genius and the capacity to self-destruct."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1028
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6962
  - "A Bishop Rethinks Sexuality" Guests: Neuhaus, Richard John.: Spong, John Shelby., 8 June 1988 (Item Program Number S0782, 1805)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 129: 5
    Program details: Put on your flak helmets for this one: Bishop Spong, in calm, reasonable tones, argues for, oh, nothing more than a complete remaking of Christian sexual morality ("The issue is that we live in the 20th century.... What we have done in our society is to separate puberty from marriage by ten to fifteen years with no corresponding ethic to tell young people how to deal with sexual energy ... Do you think they're going to refrain from sexual activity? I think they're not, and therefore I suggest that we find a way to enter into that world and provide a relationship that can be a committed relationship and have an aspect of holiness about it"). Pastor Neuhaus does not pretend to take a detached view ("Why do you want to take a Christian position when the argument of your book is that there is nothing normative about the Christian Scriptures or the Christian tradition?"). A high-voltage exchange, generating light as well as much heat.
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1025
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6959
  - "Shaking Up the Republican Party" Guests: Kean, Thomas H.: Dowd, William., 6 July 1988 (Item Program Number S0783, 1806)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 129: 6
    Transcript: Box/Folder 182: 16
    Program details: Mr. Kean--who would be the keynote speaker at the Republican convention the following month--had indeed shaken up his party with his landslide re-election three years earlier, in which he had won 60 per cent of the black vote and two-thirds of the union vote. Was the secret of his success a "laudable politics of inclusion"? Or was it--as some Republicans protesting his choice as keynote speaker argued--that he was a Democrat in Republican's clothing? Or was it simply his personal attractiveness, which comes through clearly on this show? A low-key but interesting discussion of a moderate's views: "I found a simple fact, and that is that crime is much greater in the black community than anywhere else in the state, so if you stress law and order, blacks are just as concerned about that if not more concerned than anybody else."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1029
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6963
  - "The Right to Make Fun of Public Figures" Guests: Falwell, Jerry.: Pilpel, Harriet F., 6 July 1988 (Item Program Number S0784, 1807)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 129: 7
    Program details: Hustler had published a satire which included Jerry Falwell having sexual relations with his own mother, and Mr. Falwell had sued. Some had expected the Rehnquist Court to take the opportunity to modify the "New York Times rule" on libel suits involving public figures, but instead of softening the rule it held that obvious satire does not constitute "reckless disregard for the truth." This show offers a crackling debate on the whole subject of civil liberties versus individuals' rights. JF: "Had the ad been of Harriet and her mother or father, I rather think she might be sitting where I'm sitting today rather than there defending the issue." WFB: "No, actually she wouldn't, because Harriet is a very principled woman, and she would, I think incorrectly, feel that this was a sacrifice necessary to sustain the vitality of the First Amendment."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1030
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6964
  - "How Does It Go with Deregulation of the Airlines?" Guests: Borman, Frank.: Kahn, Alfred E. (Alfred Edward), 29 June 1988 (Item Program Number S0785, 1808)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 129: 8
    Transcript: Box/Folder 182: 17
    Program details: Mr. Kahn had been the principal force behind airline deregulation in the 1970s (see Firing Line s0337); Mr. Borman had been one of its chief opponents. Mr. Borman now says: "I think the experiment's worked extremely well.... I read somewhere that in 1977 only 25 percent of Americans had flown. This year, 75 per cent have flown. So we really have made available a wonderful facility to people who in any other country in the world can't enjoy it." A good-tempered discussion of how free-market theory actually plays out in people's lives.
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1026
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6960
  - "When Should We Step Aside and Let Death Take Over?" Guests: Callahan, Daniel.: Etzioni, Amitai., 29 June 1988 (Item Program Number S0786, 1809)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 129: 9
    Program details: An absorbing and intensely disturbing discussion of medical ethics and the aged. Mr. Callahan starts from the fact that a tremendous amount of money is spent on medical procedures in what proves to be the last year of a patient's life. He also points out that, "by constantly trying to extend lives and find more and more ways to apply the technology to the elderly ... we're not getting a happier group of elderly, we're getting an elderly more fearful of growing old and more fearful of death." He finds the expenditures essentially unfair to the young and would "set limits"--apparently an arbitrary age--after which certain procedures could not be done. Mr. Etzioni fairly sputters with indignation but makes some good points about allocation of resources. We may not wind up completely agreeing with either, but we will be left with a great deal to think about."
    Availability: Not available. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1027
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/6961
  - "The French-American Connection: Accord or Discord?" Guests: Francois-Poncet, Jean.: Wahl, Nicholas., 24 August 1988 (Item Program Number S0787, 1810)
    Publicity File: Box/Folder 129: 10